Ed Holland Cartoons
Ed Holland Cartoons
1965-1969
Holland, Daniel Edward.
1.75 linear ft.
Original color editorial cartoons and proofs.
2649260
Biographical History
Daniel Edward Holland (1918-2009), commonly known as Ed Holland, was an American editorial cartoonist.
Ed Holland was born in Guthrie, Kentucky on February 2, 1918. He attended David Lipscomb College (formerly the Nashville Bible School) from 1936 to 1938, followed by two years at the Chicago Academy of Fine Arts (1938-1939). Holland would later teach at the Chicago Academy of Fine Arts for many years.
Holland worked only a few years as directorial cartoonist for the Nashville Banner (1939-1941) before being called away to service as a lieutenant with the United States Army Air Force during World War II. Holland received several decorations for his service during which he participated in the invasions of Italy and Sicily. Upon his return from service in 1945, Holland began his tenure with the Chicago Tribune after Carey Orr selected him to fill the position left by John T. McCutcheon's retirement, joining Orr and John Parrish with all three sharing the responsibility of creating 14 cartoons a week. With the exception of one four year stint with the Washington Times-Herald (1950-1954), Holland remained with the Chicago Tribune throughout the duration of his career. Holland was promoted to chief editorial cartoonist at the Tribune in 1972, a position he held until his retirement in 1975.
During his career, Holland received numerous citations from the Freedoms Foundation (certificate of merit 1949; medals 1950-51 and 1958), and his cartoons were featured many times, in color, on page one of the Chicago Tribune.
Daniel Edward Holland died on August 18, 2009.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ed Holland Cartoons are divided into 2 series: Cartoons and Proofs.
Cartoons consists of 54 original editorial cartoons. Of particular interest is that these cartoons (except for one) were done in color. The cartoons in this particular collection do not address events or politics specific to Chicago but instead focus on national and foreign affairs including the Vietnam War and President Lyndon Johnson's social programs. Worth noting is Holland's harsh criticism of college students involved with demonstrations and left-wing student groups and several cartoons depicting this appear in this collection. Holland also often used a recurring Uncle Sam character. On undated cartoon in black ink with an inscription to Gladys Clements is also included.
Holland used watercolor, ink and pencil to draw the cartoons on illustration board. The Chicago Tribune published cartoons on the front page of the paper in color, therefore it is likely that is where these cartoons appeared. Notations about specific dates or days of the week appear in pencil on the front of the cartoon. Engraver stamps on the back list dates that differ from the dates on the front of the cartoons (typically preceding the date on the front as the engraver most likely received the cartoon in advance of its publication). For purposes of this inventory, dates appearing on the front have been used to date the individual cartoons except where noted.
There are also 21 color Proofs of cartoons published in the Chicago Tribune during 1966. All but one proof lists the specific date the cartoon appeared. Five of the proofs were printed on newsprint.
Arrangement of the Collection
The cartoons and proofs are arranged in chronological order.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Holland, Daniel Edward.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States. Congress -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Chicago tribune.; Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cartoonists -- Illinois.; College students -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Demonstrations -- -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Student movements -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1963-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Proofs (printed matter); Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ed Holland, 1967-1969.
Inventory
- Cartoons, 54 13 1/4" x 15 1/4"; Click here for a detailed inventory by date. See below for an index to the cartoons.
  - Cartoons, 1965 (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
  - Cartoons, 1966 (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
  - Cartoons, 1967 (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
  - Cartoons, 1968 Jan - Mar; 1968 May - Jun (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
  - Cartoons, 1968 Aug - Oct (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
  - Cartoons, 1969 Feb; 1969 Apr - Jul (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
  - Cartoons, 1969 Aug - Sep; 1969 Nov (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
  - Cartoons, undated; 15" x 23"; black and white ink cartoon with caption "Starting a Forest Fire" inscribed "To Gladys Clements with my best wishes Ed Holland" (Map-case 1, Drawer 100)
- Proofs
  - Proofs, 1966 (Oversize 1)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
academic freedom B1F5
Albania B1F6
anti-missile systems B1F6
Berlin Wall B1F1
Brezhnev, Leonid Ilyich B1F3
China B1F6
college students B1F1 B1F3 B1F5-B1F6
communism B1F6-B1F7
Congress B1F2 B1F4 B1F6-B1F7
cost of living B1F3 B1F6
crime B1F5
criminals B1F4
Cuba B1F1
Democratic Party B1F5
demonstrations B1F1 B1F3 B1F6
Dominican Republic B1F1
drug use B1F5
Egypt B1F7
farming B1F1
foreign policy B1F7
Freeman, Orville B1F1
Ghandi, Indira B1F2
Great Society B1F1-B1F2
Harriman, W. Averell B1F4
transportation B1F7
Ho Chi Minh B1F2-B1F4 B1F6-B1F7
Humphrey, Hubert B1F5
India B1F2
inflation B1F3 B1F6-B1F7
Israel B1F3 B1F7
Japan B1F7
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B1F1-B1F5
Kennedy, Robert F. B1F3
Kennedy, Ted B1F6
labor B1F3
Latin America B1F1 B1F3
MacArthur, Douglas B1F4
McCarthy, Eugene B1F5
McNamara, Robert B1F2
Medicaid B1F6
Medicare B1F6
Middle East B1F3
Nixon, Richard M. B1F4-B1F5 B1F7
Panama Canal B1F3
patriotism B1F3
peace B1F2 B1F4 B1F6-B1F7
Percy, Charles H. B1F6
pollution B1F7
Reagan, Ronald B1F4-B1F5
Republican Party B1F4-B1F5
Rockefeller, Nelson B1F4-B1F5
Romney, George W. B1F4
Russia B1F3 B1F6
Shriver, Sargent B1F3
space exploration B1F3 B1F6
taxes B1F3 B1F6
Thant, U. B1F3 B1F5
trade B1F3
United Nations B1F3
USS Pueblo B1F4
Vance, Cyrus B1F4
Vietnam War B1F2-B1F7
violence B1F4
War on Poverty B1F3
Yugoslavia B1F6